<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Mandrill Plugin for Joomla!™ User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

      <surname>Dimitrov</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>compojoom.com</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>27.04.2012</pubdate>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the Mandrill plugin for Joomla. It
      does not cover any other extension available on compojoom.com .</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <article>
    <para><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>Revision 0.1</revnumber>

          <date>28.04.2012</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>
        </revision>
      </revhistory></para>
  </article>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introducing Mandrillapp.com</title>

      <para>In April 2012 Mailchimp (<link
      linkend="???">http://mailchimp.com</link>) introduced a new
      transactional email service called Mandrill (<link
      linkend="???">http://mandrillapp.com</link>). Mandrill is using the same
      optimized delivery engine that MailChimp uses for the delivery of bulk
      newsletters – slightly modified for one-to-one email. The core features
      of Mandrill are:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Uses MailChimp's awesome email delivery engine</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tracks opens and clicks</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatically adds Google Analytics tracking data to the
            URLs in the mail</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Has pretty, visual reports of the email results</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to tag the emails and see your stats filtered by
            tag</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Introducing Mandrill Plugin for Joomla</title>

      <para>Since you normally need to be a programmy nerd to use the service
      MailChimp asked us to create an integration for Mandrill's API into
      Joomla. And there you have it! You'll just need to provide your Mandrill
      API key and enable the plugin - after that all e-mails* send by Joomla
      are going to be sent trough the Mandrill API.</para>

      <para>* All extensions that use the standard Joomla API for sending
      mails will continue to function as normal and the mails will be send
      trough Mandrill. If you are using extensions that have their own Mail
      classes, then those extensions will continue to function as normal, but
      they won't use the Mandrill API</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation and Updates</title>

    <para>Installing the Mandrill plugin for Joomla is easy it is not in any
    way different than installing any other Joomla!™ extension/module/plugin
    on your site. You can read the complete instructions for installing
    Joomla!™ extensions on the <ulink
    url="http://help.joomla.org/content/view/1476/235/">official joomla help
    page</ulink> .Throughout this chapter we assume that you are familiar with
    these instructions and we will not duplicate them.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting the installation packages</title>

      <para>You can download the latest installation packages by visiting our
      site at <ulink
      url="https://compojoom.com">https://compojoom.com</ulink>. (you need to
      be login) In the download menu you will see the Mandrill menu item.
      Click on it. The latest releases are listed with the newest release
      always on top. Click on the release number and then download the ZIP
      package.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Compatibility</title>

        <para>The Mandrill Plugin for Joomla is compatible with Joomla
        2.5</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Updating to the latest version</title>

      <para>The plugin uses the standard update routine in Joomla. All you
      need to do is to go to Extensions -&gt; Extension Manager -&gt; Update
      in your Joomla backend. Then click on "Find Updates" if a new version of
      the plugin is available you will be able to update by selecting it and
      clicking on the "Update" button</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the Mandrill Plugin for Joomla</title>

    <para>To manage the plugin go to your Extension - Plugin manager and find
    the "System - Mandrill" plugin. Select the plugin and click on the "Edit"
    option on the top right of your screen. After that you should presented
    with a screen similar to this one:</para>

    <para><graphic fileref="images/config_screen.PNG" width="0"/></para>

    <para>In the API key field provide your Mandrill API key (on the day of
    writing that documentation the API key could be found by clicking on the
    settings button (top right) at the mandrillapp.com page (you need to be
    logged in to see it))</para>

    <para>The use https option defines if the plugin should communicate with
    Mandrill server through an SSL connection or not. We recommend to set this
    option to yes if your hosting has the necessary php ssl libraries for
    this.</para>

    <para>Once you've provided a valid API key, you can enable the plugin.
    That's it! now your Joomla site should be sending e-mails using the
    Mandrill API. You can test this by going to "users -&gt; mass mail" then
    try to send a mail to your Super users. The mail that your super users are
    going to receive should be comming from the Mandrill servers.</para>

    <note>
      <para>When you send a mass mail the user that sends the mail won't
      receive a mail. This is the way the "Mass Mail" extension works in
      Joomla and has nothing to do with the Mandrill plugin</para>
    </note>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Good to know</title>

    <section>
      <title>Sending limits</title>

      <para>Depending on your Mandrill account there are different sending
      limits that apply for you. If you are a free user then this limit is
      currently 12 000 emails per month. For more information on sending
      limits please refer to <ulink
      url="http://help.mandrill.com/customer/portal/articles/464936-mailchimp-bundled-pricing">Mandrill's
      help pages</ulink>.</para>

      <para>The current implementation of the plugin checks how many emals you
      have send for the day and how big your sending limit is. If you have
      reached your sending e-mail then the plugin will fall back to the
      standard JMailer class and will send the mails according to the settings
      that you have specified in your Global Configuration (Joomla's global
      configuration. Accessible through Site -&gt; Global Configuration -&gt;
      Server -&gt; Mail Settings)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CC emails</title>

      <para>If a Joomla extension tries to send an email that has the CC
      option set, then the plugin will fallback to the standard JMailer class
      and won't use the Mandrill API.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What happens with rejected mails?</title>

      <para>In some situations the Mandrill API won't send the mail and will
      return a rejected status for it. In this case the plugin will try to
      send the mail to the recipient again, but this time using the standard
      JMailer class.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Logging</title>

      <para>The plugin uses the standard Joomla JLog class to log errors and
      warnings. The logs are saved in the folder configured in your Joomla's
      Global Configuration. The logs are splitted by Month. You can expect
      them to identify situations in which the plugin was not able to send the
      email using Mandrill's API and has fallen back to the standard JMailer
      class.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Events logged</title>

        <para>The plugin logs following events:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use of CC option for sending emails</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Daily sending quota exceeded</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Queued messages</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rejected messages</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Unsupported attachments</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tags</title>

      <para>For each Mail we try to add the following tags:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>option - identifies the Joomla component sending the
          email</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>view - identifies the view of the component sending the
          mail</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>task - identifies the task that is executed by the component
          sending the mail</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Each of this tags is added only if we are able to identify
      it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Attachments</title>

      <para>Currently the Mandrill API supports only attachments with the mime
      type image/*, text/* and application/pdf. If your joomla site is sending
      emails that contain other attachments, then the plugin will recognise
      this and will fallback to the standard JMailer class.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>The Mandrill Plugin for Joomla is released free of charge. Community
    support is available in our Forum in the Mandrill section.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
